再续上  朋友  干的不错
Keep 'em comin', pal. You're doing great.
说不定你能助我一臂之力  我在找个女人
Say, maybe you can help me. I'm lookin' for a dame.
谁不在找呢
Aren't we all?
这个人很特别  你认识她吗
This one's special. You know her?
何止认识
Know her?
我正看着她呢
I'm lookin' at her.
我怎么才遇见你
And where have you been all my life?
要说到一段历史
Talk about a slice of history.
这个佩尼贝克俱乐部
The Pennybaker Club.
可是20世纪40年代  大腕齐聚登台的地方
You know, back in the '40s, all the greats played here.
要是这些墙会说话  故事可有得说了
If these walls could talk, man, the stories they would tell.
对  不过我们唯一想听的故事是...
Yeah, but the only story we need to hear is about...
斯坦·班克斯的  胸骨有一处枪伤
Stan Banks. Single G.S.W. to the sternum.
我推断死亡时间
I'm calling the time of death
在今早6点到8点期间
between 6:00 and 8:00 this morning.
看来他试图用这个防卫
Looks like he tried to defend himself with this.
显然  没起到作用
Obviously, it didn't work.
那么是抢劫财变杀人了吗
So a robbery gone wrong?
但他的钱包  手机
Well, he still had his wallet, cell,
还有帕克斯维尔湾的房间钥匙还在  所以...
and a room key from the parksville arms, so...
口袋被掏了出来
Pockets were pulled out,
表明凶手对尸体搜了身
indicating the killer searched the body.
找什么  我们无从得知
For what, we have no idea.
奇怪了  他有一把单身公寓的钥匙
That's weird. He's got an S.R.O. key,
可他的驾照上显示他住在34号大街[富人区]
but his driver's license has him living on 34th Street.
我们去单身公寓走一趟
We'll hit the S.R.O.
看看能不能找到点他的线索
See if there's anything we can find out about him.
谢谢
Thanks.
你在找酒喝吗  卡塞尔
You lookin' for a drink, Castle?
因为我确定吧台已经关了
'Cause I'm pretty sure the bar is closed.
实际上  我在找线索
Actually, I was looking for a clue.
找到一个
I think I found one.
哪个流浪汉的小窝  还有...
Some homeless guy's squat, and...
今天的《账报》  他今天早上还在这里
today's "Ledger." He was here this morning.
不管是谁  或许他目睹了什么
Well, whoever he is, maybe he saw something.
我让巡逻小队去排查这片区域
I'll get patrol units to canvass the area.
斯坦死了
Stan's dead?
这下可好
Well, that's just great.
我该怎么处置他的这堆破玩意儿
What am I supposed to do with all his crap?
我们会先带走些东西
We'll be taking some of it off your hands
这是我们的调查职责
as part of our investigation.
你知道最近有谁在威胁斯坦吗
You know of anyone who's been threatening Stan lately?
我是这里的管理员  不是童子军的女训导员
I'm the manager here, not the den mother.
那好吧  你最近一次看到他是什么时候
Okay, then. When was the last time you saw him?
今天早上  斯坦满脸笑容
Uh, this morning. Stan was all smiles.
通知我他要搬走了
Gave notice he was moving out
因为他的船要来了[鸿运当头]
'cause his ship was coming in.
-什么船  -不知道
- What ship? - Oh, I don't know.
看现在这状况  估计是"泰坦尼克"号
The "Titanic" from the looks of things.
如果你还记起其它事
Well, if you can remember anything else,
能给我们打电话吗
can you please give me a call?
别太指望我了  帅哥
Don't hold your breath, hotshot.
我觉得她喜欢你
I think she likes you.
我不知道为什么斯坦怎么会在佩尼贝克俱乐部
I have no idea why Stan was at the Pennybaker Club.
可我们已经分居快一年了
But we've been separated for almost a year,
所以天知道他去哪里了
so god knows where he's been.
那你最后一次和他联系是什么时候
And when was the last time you spoke with him?
两个月前  说来真是疯狂
Two months ago, which is crazy,
因为以前我们两个小时不说话都不行
'cause there was a time we couldn't go two hours without talking.
可后来斯坦非要去找达布隆
But then Stan had to go and find that doubloon.
达布隆  是西班牙古币吗
A doubloon, as in old Spanish coin?
他在北卡罗来纳的一个海滩上挖到一枚
He dug one up on a beach in North Carolina.
从那以后  他就着了迷
And after that, he got the bug.
而他看了那愚蠢的纪录片后就更变本加厉了
And it only got worse after he saw this stupid documentary
讲的是克莱德·贝拉斯科  一个寻宝猎人
about Clyde Belasco, the treasure hunter.
对  就是那个人
Yeah, that's the fellow
十年前找到了沉没的南联邦船只
who found that sunken confederate ship ten years ago.
斯坦倍受鼓舞
Stan was so inspired,
他辞去会计工作  去寻找失落的古迹
he quit his accounting job to search for lost antiquities.
即便是我们上一次谈话时
I mean, even the last time we spoke,
他还是满嘴都是他离找到蓝蝴蝶
all he could talk about was how he was close
仅有一步之遥
to finding a blue butterfly.
蓝...是种昆虫吗
A blue... like an insect?
谁知道
Who knows?
在你认识的人里  他和谁有过节吗
Was he having problems with anyone that you know of?
他有债务问题  这我知道
He had money problems. I know that.
两天前  我接到一个男人的电话
I got a call two days ago from some guy
说要找斯坦
looking for Stan.
他说斯坦欠他一万块
Said that Stan owed him $10,000
还说他最好还上
and that he'd better pay
不然走着瞧
or else.
斯坦的私人物品里没有关于蝴蝶的
There's nothing in Stan's personal effects
蓝色的  和其它颜色的都没有
about butterflies, blue or otherwise.
只有一堆书
Just a bunch of books
讲的是40年代的黑帮和曼哈顿
about mobsters and Manhattan in the '40s.
没关系  我查到了
That's all right, because I got a hit
给斯坦妻子打恐吓电话的人
on that threatening money call to Stan's wife,
结果发现是一家干洗店打来的
and it turns out it came from a dry cleaners.
或许他们洗的不仅只有衣服
Maybe clothes aren't the only thing they're laundering.
我去查
I'll check it out.
谢了
Thanks.
斯坦物品里的有本日记  也是40年代的
Uh, this diary in Stan's stuff, it's also from the '40s.
听起来像是私家侦探的
It sounds like it belonged to a private eye.
听听这段
Listen to this.
"通常来说  妻子们在看到
"Usually wives turn on the waterworks
丈夫出轨的照片时会泪如雨下
when shown pictures of their husbands stepping out,
可这个女人不同
but not this dame.
她要以牙还牙  那么哪一点更糟
She wanted payback. So what's worse,
是我与一位客户共赴巫山
that I pitched woo with a client
还是我在事后为所提供的服务给她开了发票"
or that I invoiced her for services rendered after?"
挺可爱
Cute.
可爱
Cute?
这家伙给人的感觉像个无情的私家侦探
I mean, this guy sounds like a hard-boiled P.I.
就跟雷蒙德·钱德勒的小说人物似的
right out of a Raymond Chandler novel.
不知道为什么斯坦有这个
I wonder why Stan had this?
贝克特
Hey, yo, Beckett.
还是没查到那个流浪汉
Still got no word on that homeless guy,
不过有个酒店老板看见一辆白色野马
but a bodega owner saw a white Mustang
停在俱乐部门外的卸货区
parked in the loading zone right outside the club
停了三天
for the past three days.
好  去问问有没有人看到车牌
Okay. See if anyone saw those license plates.
-这就去  -好
- Right on. - Okay.
贝克特
Um, Beckett?
我今晚能把这个带回家吗
Can I take this home for the night?
或许通过这个能查到斯坦在找的东西
I mean, it might be the key to what Stan was looking for.
你只是因为觉得这个有意思才想看
You just want to read it because you think it's cool.
对  也有这原因
Yeah, well, that, too.
好  只要你...
Okay, just so long as you...
明早还回来就行
bring it back in the morning.
"1947年6月18日
"June 18, 1947.
今天像往常一样开始
The day began like every other,
在我的办公椅上醒来
pulling awake in my office chair
拿着肯塔基香酒的瓶子
with a cream of Kentucky bottle,
感觉喉咙干涩
A dry throat,
脑袋疼得叮当作响
and a head that was ringing like church bells.
于是  我决定再喝点酒
So I figured I'd kill two birds with one stone
以消宿醉  一解饥渴"
with a little hair of the dog that bit me."
该死  弗林先生
Damn it, Mr. Flynn.
你每晚在办公室
Why have an apartment
醉死过去  还要公寓干什么
when you drink yourself to sleep in the office every night?
那样的话  我就永远不会迟到了
That way, I'm never late for work.
说吧  有什么事
Say, what gives, anyhow?
我们有个潜在客户  所以客气点
We have a potential client, so be nice.
如果你不介意  我还想挣下个月的房租钱
I'd like to make next month's rent if you don't mind.
可以吗
All right?
我看上去怎么样
How do I look?
像个明星
Like a star.
"又是曼哈顿岛上平凡的一天
"Just another day on the isle of Manhattan"...
直到她走进来
Until she walked in
带来了改变我一生的案子
with a case that changed my life.
她穿着T字带斜面的鞋  和很土的衣服
Wearing t-strap shoes and a country suit,
我能看出  那个红头发女人
I could tell that that redhead
是刚进城的乡巴佬"
was a hick fresh off the cob."
你好  我叫莎莉·莫奎恩
Hello. My name's Sally Mulqueen.
我想说的是斯科菲尔德  抱歉  我刚结婚
I mean, Scofield. Sorry, I'm a newlywed.
还在适应这个新名字
Still gettin' used to the name.
我是乔·弗林  斯科菲尔德夫人
Joe Flynn, Mrs. Scofield.
说吧  你来找我有什么事
So tell me, what has you knocking on my shingle?
我劝我丈夫到纽约来度蜜月
I-I talked my husband into honeymoonin' up here in the big apple,
可不是因为我想上摩天大楼
but not because I wanted to climb skyscrapers
看百老汇表演
and see broadway shows.
我自己另有目的
I had myself another reason.
我想寻找我的姐姐薇拉
See, I'm lookin' for my big sister Vera.
薇拉·莫奎恩
Vera Mulqueen.
我们家庭不和
There was bad blood back home,
两年前薇拉离家出走
and Vera ran off two years ago
梦想在这样的大都市里做一个歌舞女郎
with dreams of being a showgirl up here in the big city.
她给你寄过电报  明信片
She send you a wire, postcard,
或者任何有回信地址的东西吗
anything with a return address?
你能找到她吗  侦探先生
Can you find her, mister?
母亲病了  而且
Mama's sick, and, um...
大概活不长久了
Doesn't have long.
他当然能够找到
Well, of course he can...
只需每日十五元外加承担所有花费
For 15 bucks a day plus expenses.
还有一个条件
Only...
此事能否不要声张
can we keep this quiet?
如我之前所说  我们家庭不和
Like I said, there's bad blood back home,
如果薇拉从陌生人口中得知
and if Vera hears from a stranger
家人在寻找她
that the family's looking for her,
或许她会逃得更远
it might push her farther away.
斯科菲尔德夫人
Mrs. Scofield,
我是最谨慎小心的人了
if I'm anything, I'm discreet.
"那是我第一次见到她
"And that's when I saw her.
看着那张照片  我的脑海中只有一个念头
Looking at that photograph, all I could think was,
多么美的女人
what a beautiful doll.
莎莉说薇拉想要成为一个歌舞女郎
Sally said Vera had dreams of being a showgirl.
或许她实现了自己的愿望
Maybe she made it.
那也不会是这城市里最奇怪的事情
Stranger things have happened in this town.
我的最后一站去了佩尼贝克俱乐部
My last stop was the Pennybaker club."
我本希望看到我最喜欢的表演者沙奇摩的演出
I was hoping my favorite performer Satchmo was blowing."
但是似乎没有这么好运
But no such luck.
但是我并不抱怨
Couldn't complain, though,
因为站在台上的是贝西·辛克莱
because Betsy Sin clair was up there,
她的歌喉宛如天籁"
and that songbird's got golden pipes."
威士忌
Whiskey.
"走遍了全城
"I'll be damned if all that walking
我屁股里的弹片都要闹了
didn't get the shrapnel in my hip buzzing.
幸好我知道哪里能找到我的解药"
But I knew where to get my medicine."
说不定你能助我一臂之力  我在找个女人
Say, maybe you can help me. I'm lookin' for a dame.
谁不在找呢
Aren't we all?
这个人很特别  你认识她吗
This one's special. You know her?
何止认识
Know her?
我正看着她呢
I'm lookin' at her.
我怎么才遇见你
And where have you been all my life?
"我怎么想的啊
"What was I thinking?
这个女人简直就是一个会走路的麻烦
This dame was trouble on two legs.
我一直告诉自己不要盯着她看
I kept telling myself to look away.
她跟汤姆·丹普西在一起  这个家伙简直是
She was with Tom Dempsey, for crying out loud--
纽约市有史以来最残忍冷酷的黑帮头目
the most ruthless mob boss new york has ever given birth to.
丹普西派了两个手下来
Dempsey sent over two of his gorillas--
一个爱尔兰人
an irishman,
和一个像从哪个哈瓦那黑帮借来的古巴人"
and a cuban on loan from some Havana mob family."
老大想要见你  小子
The boss wants to see you, boy-o.
不好意思  伙计们
Sorry, boys.
我的舞伴预约已经满了
My dance card's full.
我们不是在跟你商量  朋友
This isn't a request, compadre.
你知道我是谁吗
You know who I am?
服务生吗  我想要一杯威士忌
The waiter? I'll take a whiskey.
这两个小伙子可以共享一杯黑刺杜李松子酒
The boys here can share a sloe gin fizz.
你给我小心点  小子
Better watch yourself, there, boy-o.
小心说话  否则割了你的舌头
Hold your tongue, or I'll cut it out.
耍聪明啊
Mm, a wise guy.
我讨厌耍聪明的人
I hate wise guys
就像我讨厌那些盯着我的女人看的废物
about as much as I hate crumbs eyeballing my girl.
这很粗鲁  没有礼貌
It's rude, uncivil.
不过没有关系  朋友
That's all right, friend.
我的手下会好好调教你的
The boys are gonna teach you some lessons.
好了  臭小子  第一课
Okay, boy-o, first lesson.
来  抓住他
Over here. Get him.
"就这样
"There I was,
挂着一身的残羹冷炙
covered in the discards of the blue plate special,
我问自己  这么做值还是不值
asking myself, 'was it worth it?
绝对值
It was.
为了她不论怎么挨打都是值得的"
She was worth every punch."
你受伤了吗
Are you hurt?
这点伤吗
What, this?
根本不算什么
It's nothin'.
你该看看我的脸把那家伙的拳头伤得多厉害
You should see what my face did to the other guy's fist.
那你叫什么名字  硬汉
So what's your name, tough guy?
这要紧吗  美人
Does it matter, doll?
薇拉
Vera!
你知道你戴着老大的东西
You know you're not supposed to leave our sight
不能离开我们的视线
with the boss' hardware on.
那个蓝蝴蝶
The blue butterfly.
是一条项链
It's a necklace.
这就是斯坦·班克斯被杀的原因
That's why Stan Banks was killed.
我干嘛要独白啊
Why am I narrating?
干洗店的勒索电话有什么线索了吗
So anything on that threatening call to the dry cleaners?
店主说他根本不知道斯坦
Yeah, the owner claims he doesn't know anything about Stan
或者什么蓝蝴蝶
or blue butterflies.
但是一个叫雷·霍顿的人租用了后面的房间
However, a guy named Ray Horton rents out a back room.
而且雷是正在假释中的收注人
Turns out Ray is a bookie on parole.
可能斯坦跟雷约在佩尼贝克见面
Okay, so maybe Stan was trying to meet Ray at the Pennybaker
为了偿还他的赌债
so that he could pay off some debts?
斯坦去那里不是为了还债
Uh, Stan was not there because of his debt.
他去那里也不是为了哪只蓝蝴蝶
He was not even there about a blue butterfly.
而是为了那条蓝蝴蝶
He was there about the blue butterfly.
是一条项链
It's a necklace.
一个蝴蝶图案的装饰品  完全由
A butterfly-shaped centerpiece made entirely of...
蓝钻镶嵌
blue diamonds
价值轻松达到一百万
worth about a million dollars, easy.
你是从哪发现这些的
Where are you getting all of this?
从那个私家侦探的日记
Fron whe P.I.'s diary.
所以斯坦是在寻找宝物了
So Stan was on a treasure hunt.
正是  我还做了一个小调查
Exactly. I did a little research.
这个蓝蝴蝶宝石在四十年代时失踪了
It turns out the blue butterfly disappeared sometime in the '40s,
有传言说  它藏在佩尼贝克俱乐部的某处
And rumor has it, it's hidden somewhere in the Pennybaker club.
如果他找到了它
If he found it...
价值百万的项链  杀人动机不是很明显了么
A million-dollar necklace? Talk about motive for murder.
对了  莱恩  说小子
By the way, Ryan, say boy-o.
-小子  -小子
- Boy-o. - Boy-o.
- Boy- o. - Boy-o.
-小子  -算了
- Boy- o. - Anyway.
在网上搜索了一下
Did some searching on the net.
相关信息并不多
There wasn't a lot there.
但是我发现  项链据说被诅咒了
But I found, it's supposedly cursed,
曾经属于某位纳粹党卫军官员的情妇
and at one time belonged to an S.S. Officer's mistress.
战后  项链流入到美国
After the war, made its way stateside
到了黑帮大佬汤姆·丹普西的手里
and into the hands of mob boss Tom Dempsey,
同时也是这家俱乐部的主人  因此我们得回去
who owned the club, which is why we need to go back.
-我们要回去  -是的
- We do? - Yeah.
你还记得我们在斯坦手里找到的绿色铁棒么
You remember the, uh, green rod we found in Stan's hand?
丹普西俱乐部楼下的办公室
Apparently, Dempsey's downstairs office
涂了酢浆草绿色的漆
was painted shamrock green.
斯坦肯定下去过
Stan had to have gone down there.
而且根据日记  蓝蝴蝶正是被保存在
Also, according to the diary, the blue butterfly was kept
丹普西办公室的秘密保险箱里
in a secret safe in Dempsey's office.
我们很可能漏掉了什么
It's very possible we missed something.
因为我们根本没有好好地看过那里
We never really looked down there.
莱恩  你继续追查看能否找到那个收注人
Okay, Ryan, you see if you can get ahold of the bookie.
-卡塞尔和我会去犯罪现场  -好的
- Castle and I will go back to the crime scene. - Okay.
-小子  -小子
- Boy-o. - Boy-o.
-发音要像小妖精一样  -卡塞尔
- Like a leprechaun. - Castle.
抱歉
Sorry.
私家侦探告诉莎莉
So the P.I. tells Sally
她在佩尼贝克俱乐部找到了她姐姐
that he found her sister here at the Pennybaker club.
莎莉有去找她姐姐吗
And did Sally go talk to her sister?
没有  乔认为莎莉
Well, no. Joe could tell that Sally,
这样一个来自乡下的单纯的女孩
being an innocent girl from the country,
她与黑帮打交道会无所适从
she was a little bit nervous about dealing with mobsters,
因此他自愿回去联系薇拉
So he offered to go back and make contact with Vera.
我敢肯定他是出自好心
Out of the goodness of his heart, I'm sure.
你能怪他吗  我是说  她太美了
Can you blame the guy? I mean, she was gorgeous.
不管怎样  乔告诉莎莉他会安排她们会面
So anyway, Joe tells Sally he's gonna go arrange a meeting.
莎莉同意了  但再次坚持乔不要告诉薇拉
Sally agreed, but again, insisted that Joe not tell Vera
是她在找她
that she was looking for her
因为家里那些宿怨的缘故
because of all the animosity back home.
我是对的
Ah. I was right.
我打赌这就是他拿到那根铁棒的地方
I bet that's where he got the steel rod,
他可能是想用来撬开秘密保险箱
which is probably what he used to pry open the secret safe.
我也不想戳破你的美梦  卡塞尔
Hate to burst bubbles, Castle,
但是这个已经很多年没放过东西了
but this hasn't held anything in years.
看来斯坦失望而归了
Looks like Stan was disappointed.
是的  如果那就是秘密保险箱他或许会失望
Yeah, he probably would've been if that was the secret safe.
那不是秘密保险箱吗
That's not the secret safe?
告诉你一个有趣的事实
Here's a fun fact--
人们通常有两个保险箱
people often kept two safes,
一个放些价值不高的东西  且容易被找到
one that was easy to find for minor valuables,
另一个就没那么容易找到了
and a second safe that was much harder to locate
放着更贵重的东西  比如蓝蝴蝶
for the extra specials, like blue butterflies.
卡塞尔  秘密保险箱在哪里
Castle, where's the secret safe?
马上就说到
Coming to that.
乔和薇拉相识已经五天了
So it's five days since Joe and Vera met.
而他们已经深深地爱上了对方
And they were very much in love.
只过了五天  拜托
After only five days? Come on.
在40年代人们不浪费一点时间
Well, people didn't waste time back in the '40s.
事实上  他们情到深处
Matter of fact, they were so much in love...
已然不顾一切了
well, they risked it all.
那这和我们的秘密保险箱有什么关系
So what does that have to do with our secret safe?
一切就发生在后台
And it happened backstage...
就在楼上
right upstairs.
他们两人正在幽会
They were stealing a moment together,
这很危险  因为她是丹普西的女人
which was dangerous, because she was Dempsey's girl.
当他们四目相对之时
As they stared into each other's eyes,
凯特心跳加快
Kate's heart quickened.
你刚是不是说了"凯特"
Did you just say "Kate"?
你是不是把自己想象成私家侦探
Are you picturing the PI as you
把我想象成黑老大的情妇
and me as the gangster's moll?
什么  没有
What? No.
我没有说"凯特"
And I didn't say "Kate."
我说的是"命运"  "命运的心跳加快"
I said "Fate." "Fate's heart quickened."
我只是想诗意一点  老天
I was being poetic. God.
总之就如我所说的
Anyway, as I was saying,
正当他们要接吻的时候
they were just about to kiss when...
嘿呦  臭小子
Oye, chico!
是谁
Who's that?
怎么了  小子  没长教训啊
Hey, boy-o. You must be a slow learner.
我的宝贝原来这这里
There's my baby.
他和你是一对吗  辛克莱小姐
He's with you, Miss Sinclair?
是的
Yes,
而且你们那天晚上
and I don't appreciate you lugs
打得他满地找牙  我很生气
mopping the floor with him the other night.
不是没原因的  但你得低调一点
Not for nothin', but you need to keep this on the hush-hush.
丹普西不喜欢黑白配
Dempsey's not too keen about mixed laundry.
那就作为我们之间的小秘密
Well, then we'll just keep this our little secret.
你们说呢
What do you say?
好了  伙计们
All right, fellas.
你最好放聪明一点  薇拉
You better wise up, Vera.
如果被丹普西发现他会把你大卸八块的
Dempsey will have you butchered if he finds out.
他虽说吻技了得
I mean, he's a hell of a smoocher and all,
但是该死的  姑娘
but, damn it, girl,
这小白脸真值得你如此吗
is this yum-yum really worth it?
他就是我的心头肉
He's the cream in my coffee.
你俩真像故事里的主角
You two are a walking fairy tale.
我的老天爷
Good lord.
走吧
Come on.
要知道贝西说得对
Betsy's right, you know?
丹普西发现我们的事  定会杀了我们
Dempsey will scrag us for sure if he catches us turtle-doving.
你必须要带我离开这儿  乔
You gotta get me away from here, Joe,
离开丹普西  离开这一切
away from Dempsey, away from all of it.
然后去哪里呢  我们能逃得了一时
Oh, yeah, and go where? We can blow this town, sure.
等到我们身无分文的时候还能逃多远呢
Only how far are we gonna get when we're both flat broke?
我们不会的  乔
We're not broke, Joe.
我脖子上戴的东西远远超过我们所需要的了
We've got all the money we need and more around my neck.
我们只要带着它走就足够了
All we gotta do is take it away with us.
什么  你疯了吗
What, are you daffy?
你戴着它的时候起码有两个保镖
You got at least two Brunos with you at all times
跟着你形影不离
when you're wearing that thing.
说来也好笑
It's funny.
当我还是个卖烟女的时候
Back when I was a cigarette girl,
我看到丹普西和他的女友
I'd watch Dempsey coming in with his girlfriend
脖子上戴着它走进来
wearing this thing around her neck,
我想得到它
and I wanted it.
没过多久  我成为了他的女人我也得到了它
Pretty soon, I was his girl and I had it.
但这不只是一个项链  它是一个钻石做的枷锁
But it's not a necklace, Joe. It's a diamond noose,
而我越来越喘不过气了
and it's getting harder to breathe.
那我们就要把这个枷锁变成救命索
Then we gotta turn that noose into a lifeline.
问题是怎样变
The question is, how?
我不戴时  丹普西把它放在一个秘密保险箱里
When I'm not wearing it, Dempsey keeps it in a secret safe,
而我知道在哪里
and I know where it is.
然后呢
And?
然后
And...
就没了
that's it.
这是日记的最后一篇
That was the last entry in the diary.
什么叫没了  那乔怎么样了
What do you mean, that's it? What happened to Joe?
-薇拉怎么样了  -我不知道
- What happened to Vera? - I don't know.
你不知道结局为什么还要告诉我这个故事
Well, why would you tell a story when you don't know the ending?
如果你想听有头有尾的故事
If you wanted a beginning and a middle and an end,
我有27本小说供你选择
I have 27 novels you can choose from.
好吧  那这个秘密保险箱在哪里
Okay, so where is this secret safe?
我不知道  但我认为斯坦肯定找到了
I don't know, but I think Stan must have found it.
也许这就是他需要那根棒子的原因
Maybe that's why he needed that rod,
为了撬开一面墙什么的
to pry open a wall or something.
卡塞尔  看这个板条
Castle, look at the molding.
怎么回事
What...
没有锁上
It's unlocked.
斯坦找到了
Stan found it.
所以他才被杀了
That's why he was killed.
但谁杀了他呢
But by whom?
雷·霍顿
Ray Horton.
伤人  斗殴  而现在你用干洗店
Assault, battery, and now you're using a dry cleaners
做你赌博生意的幌子
to front your bookmaking operation.
等等  慢点
Whoa. Slow your roll.
我这样的假释犯是不能搀和赌博的
A man on parole like myself can't be mixed up in bookmaking.
那凶杀呢  雷
How about murder, Ray?
你能搀和凶杀吗
Is it okay to get mixed up in that?
斯坦
Stan?
是谁杀了他
And who--who killed him?
我吗
Me?
我为什么要杀我的合伙人
Why would I kill my business partner?
你的合伙人  别扯了
Your business partner? Come on.
是真的  老兄
It's true, man.
是我的一个客户介绍的
One of my clients hooked us up.
他知道我想扩大投资
He knew that I was looking to diversify
而斯坦需要资金去找一条失踪的项链
and that Stan needed financing to find this lost necklace.
斯坦告诉我他需要一万块的开销
Stan told me he needed 10 g's for expenses
去买一个旧私家侦探的日记
and to buy this old private detective's diary.
所以我同意出资赞助他  分一半利润
So I agreed to back him for half the profits.
如果这是真的  你为什么要威胁斯坦的妻子
Well, if that's true, then why did you threaten Stan's wife?
因为斯坦躲着我  我以为我被耍了
Because Stan was ducking me. I thought I got played.
两天以后他找到我
Then he came up to me two days ago,
告诉我了来龙去脉
and he told me what was up.
他说他找到了那个能补全蓝蝴蝶之谜
He said he found the man with the missing piece
缺失的线索的人
of the puzzle to the blue butterfly.
-那个人是谁  -我不知道
- And who's this man? - I don't know.
但是如果斯坦找到了蓝蝴蝶
But if Stan found the blue butterfly,
大概就是这个人杀了他
that's probably who killed him.
我追查了那本日记  斯坦调查得很深入
So I traced the diary. Stan did his research.
他从乔以前的秘书的孙女手中
He purchased it from the granddaughter
买下了这本日记
of Joe's old secretary,
一个叫做露丝·亨特沙克的女人
A woman by the name of Ruth Huntsacker.
那又怎样
So?
我和亨特沙克太太谈过
So I spoke to Mrs. Huntsacker.
她说她可能还有私家侦探的一些旧文件
she said, she might still have some of the PI's old papers
也许那些文件能告诉我们到底发生了什么
and they might be able to tell us what happened.
她会让她儿子找找看
She's gonna have her son look for them
然后再联系我
and then call me back.
听着  卡塞尔  我承认乔和薇拉的故事
Look, Castle, I admit that Joe and Vera's story
很有趣也很浪漫
is fun and romantic,
但是发生在1947年的事情
but whatever happened back in 1947
和斯坦的凶手没有一点关系
has nothing to do with who murdered Stan.
这我可不确定
Uh... I'm not so sure about that.
收注人的不在场证明证实了
Our bookie alibied out.
但弹道报告出来了  我们找到了匹配结果
But ballistics came in, and we got a match.
杀死斯坦的点38口径左轮手枪
The 38-caliber revolver that killed Stan
曾一枪夺两命  案子至今未破
was used in an unsolved double homicide
而且那是1947年
in 1947.
我就知道两者有联系
I knew there was a connection.
死者都是谁
Who were the victims?
一个叫做薇拉·莫奎恩的女子
Uh, some lady named vera mulqueen
和一个叫做乔·弗林私家侦探
and a private detective named Joe Flynn.
被杀
Murdered.
真是太惨了
That's too bad.
我真的以为那对疯狂的恋人能逃出生天呢
I really thought those two crazy kids were gonna make it.
是啊  确实不是我所期待的结局
Yeah, not exactly the ending I was hoping for.
我都不知道那么早就有弹道报告了
I didn't even know ballistics went back that far.
是啊  从二十年代就有了
Oh, yeah. Since the 20s.
案子毕竟有年月了  系统里的资料有限
Being that it's an old case, there's not much in the system.
乔·弗林和薇拉·莫奎恩的遗骸
The remains of Joe Flynn and Vera Mulqueen
被发现时在弗林的车里
were found in Flynn's car.
就停在佩尼贝克俱乐部的后巷
It was parked in the ally of the Pennybaker club.
两名死者都是被38口径左轮手枪打死
Both victims were shot with a .38 revolver
车被人点着了
and the car was set on fire.
唯一的嫌疑人是汤姆·丹普西
Only suspect was Tom Dempsey,
但找不到足够证据拘捕他
but there was never enough evidence to arrest.
我敢说是丹普西发现他们两人
You know what? I bet you Dempsey caught the two of them
预谋一起逃跑  就杀了他俩
trying to run away together, and he killed them.
但是斯坦的凶手是怎么
But how does Stan's killer
在六十年后拿到丹普西的枪呢
get Dempsey's gun 60 years later?
除非...
Unless...
就是丹普西杀了斯坦
Dempsey killed Stan.
他现在该有九十了吧  不过也是有可能的
He'd be, what, like 90 years old, but it's still possible?
不可能是丹普西
Couldn't have been Dempsey.
他死于心脏病
He died of a heart attack
就在乔和薇拉被杀后四个月
four months after Joe and Vera were killed.
不过呢...
Still...
我们还是该去把1947年的那份案宗调出来
we should dig up that 1947 police report.
里面或许有关于枪的一些记录
There could be something in there about the gun
能帮我们侦破斯坦的凶案
that could shed some light on Stan's murder.
好吧  我去仓库
All right. I'll go to the warehouse
把以前的案宗调出来
and I'll pull up the old case files.
我也想去
Oh, oh, uh, I want to go.
好吧
Uh, okay.
-我开车行吗  -随你便
- Can I drive? - I don't care.
是这样...
So...
我刚刚查了曾属于丹普西的枪支
I did a search of guns Dempsey used to own.
结果发现曾举办过一次资产出售
Turns out there was an estate sale
一个名叫克莱德·贝拉斯科的寻宝猎人
where a treasure hunter named Clyde Belasco
买下了丹普西所有的枪  包括两把38口径
bought all of Dempsey's firearms, including 2 .38s.
等等  克莱德·贝拉斯科吗
Wait. Clyde Belasco?
斯坦的妻子说
Stan's wife said that
他们俩看了一部关于他的纪录片
the two of them watched a documentary about him,
而斯坦因此受到鼓舞变成了一个寻宝猎人
and that inspired Stan to become a treasure hunter.
联系还不止于此
Well, the connections don't stop there.
贝拉斯科一周前从法国飞入境
Belasco flew in from France a week ago,
我刚刚找到一篇文章说
and I just found an article that said
他找蓝蝴蝶已经有十五年了
that he searched for the Blue Butterfly for 15 years.
那个收注人说斯坦找到一个
That bookie said that Stan found someone
有缺失的那部分线索的人
who had the missing piece of the puzzle.
或许贝拉斯科就是那个人
Well, maybe Belasco's that someone.
在这儿呢
Here it is.
最近有人擦过上面的灰尘
This has been dusted off recently.
看来我们不是唯一对本案感兴趣的人
Looks like we're not the only ones interested in this case.
斯坦来过这儿  肯定是他
Stan was here. Had to be.
你想啊  日记  凶案
Think about it--the diary, the murders...
我们只是在跟着他的脚印前行
All we're doing is walking in his footsteps.
这就是下一条线索
This is the next piece of the puzzle.
薇拉和私家侦探遇害现场的照片
Huh. Crime scene photo of Vera and the P.I.
该死的  乔
Damn it, Joe.
老伙计
You old sap.
爱上一个女孩  害得自己身陷火海
Dizzy with a dame and got yourself cooked.
鲍嘉先生  我们到底要找什么呢
So, Mr. Bogart, what exactly are we looking for here?
1947年的那起凶案和现在的这起
Our 1947 murders and our present-day murder
之间的联系肯定不仅仅是那支枪
have to be connected by more than just a gun.
这里面就能找到别的联系
Somewhere in here is that connection.
是啊  我的确买了几支汤姆·丹普西的左轮
Yes, I bought several of Tom Dempsey's revolvers.
你们如果愿意  大可去检查每一把
And by all means, test fire every last one of them as you wish.
我们会的  好了  说说你跟斯坦怎么认识的
We will. Now... how do you know Stan?
你必须了解我是上过电视的人
You have to understand that I'm on television.
也有写我的文章
Articles are written about me.
因此  有些业余人士会登门找我
Because of this, the amateurs come a-knocking.
这是我的职业危害
It's an occupational hazard.
那么斯坦来找你是为了什么呢
And what was the purpose of Stan's visit?
当然是冲着蓝蝴蝶来的
Why, the Blue Butterfly, of course.
他肯定是读到了我费尽心思在找它
He must have read of my exploits searching for it
就跑来用他荒谬的故事烦我
and decided to burden me with his preposterous story.
什么故事
And what story was that?
他说他找到了一本旧私家侦探的日记
That he had found an old private investigator's diary,
里面有缺失的线索
which held missing clues.
你不相信吗
You didn't believe him?
当然不
Of course not.
我要求看这本传说中的日记时  他拒绝了
When I asked to see the alleged diary, he refused.
却要求看我对佩尼贝克俱乐部的所有研究
And yet, he wanted access to all my research on the Pennybaker club.
说真的  整件事都很荒谬
I mean, really, the whole thing was absurd.
他甚至要求从后面走
He even asked to exit out the back door.
说有辆车在跟踪他
Said a car was following him.
是一辆白色的野马
It was a white mustang.
大概还有别人也对蓝蝴蝶有兴趣
I guess someone else was interested in the Blue Butterfly, too.
感觉像是海底捞针
It feels like we're looking for a needle in a haystack,
不过我们连海都没找到呢
except for, we can't find the haystack.
要是找到了针还要海何用
Who needs a haystack when the needle is right here?
这是一份乔的秘书肯纳德太太的口供
This is a statement from Joe's secretary Mrs. Kennard.
就在他死后记录下来的
It was taken right after his death.
"福劳伦斯·肯纳德太太
"Mrs. Florence Kennard,
死者乔·弗林的秘书
secretary to the victim Joe Flynn,
作证称目睹了下面这段发生于
attested to bearing witness to the following conversation
1947年6月24日早晨  两位死者间的对话
between both victims on the morning of June 24, 1947."
我办法都想尽了  宝贝
I've worked this from every angle, doll.
我们不可能打开丹普西的秘密保险箱的
There's no way we can crack Dempsey's secret safe.
那我们要怎么拿到
Well, then how are we gonna get it?
简单  你今晚要戴着它走出来
Easy. You're gonna walk right out the door with it tonight.
怎么做  今早甩掉丹普西的走狗就很难了
How? It was hard enough shaking Dempsey's hatchet men this morning.
我戴着蓝蝴蝶的时候会更难的
It's gonna be that much harder when I'm wearing the Blue Butterfly.
相信我  会轻而易举的
It'll be a cakewalk. Trust me.
特别是我们还有好朋友吉米·度耶相助
Especially with our friend Jimmy Doyle helping us out.
-吉米·度耶是谁  -他是个职业拳击手
- And who's Jimmy Doyle? - He's a prizefighter,
而今晚他要迎战舒格·雷·罗宾逊
and tonight he's taking on Sugar Ray Robinson
争夺次中量级冠军
for the welterweight title.
那又如何
So?
那么每个值得尊敬的喜欢苜蓿的爱尔兰佬
So every clover-loving Irishman worth his salt
今晚都会凑在收音机前
will be huddled around a radio tonight,
为吉米呐喊助威
cheering good ol' Jimmy on.
你等到比赛正酣的时候
You're gonna wait till a rousing part of the fight.
借故离开
Then you're gonna excuse yourself.
不管是谁被指派盯着你
Whoever's assigned to be watching you
肯定不会留意你的动向
surely won't be paying much attention.
你趁这时从后门溜走
That's when you slip right out the back door,
而我会在那里等你
where I'll be waiting for you.
乔
Oh, Joe.
这真是太好了
It's perfect.
不  这太疯狂了
No, it's crazy.
你在想什么啊  弗林先生
What are you thinkin', Mr. Flynn?
我告诉你  这姑娘是祸水
And I can tell you, this Jane's no good.
你在说什么啊
Now what are you on about?
看看我  我脱胎换骨  比以前强多了
Look at me. I'm a new man. I'm a better man.
自从我遇见薇拉我滴酒未沾
I haven't even had a drink since I met Vera,
如果这还不算个奇迹  那什么是奇迹
And if that's not a minor miracle, I don't know what is.
你泡在酒精里也比
You would be better off with the booze
泡在她怀里强
than with this chippy.
你们的恋情是构建在什么样的基础上呢
A-and what are you basing a relationship on, huh,
豪夺和谎言吗
a robbery and a lie?
什么谎言
What lie?
我想现在该向你坦白了
Well, I guess it's time to come clean, huh?
听我说  宝贝
Look, doll,
那晚我们在俱乐部相见并非巧合
it's no coincidence I met you in the club that night.
我是受人雇用去找你的
I was hired to come find you, see?
但我不能告诉你雇主是谁
Only I couldn't tell you who.
这是...
It's just...
别拐弯抹角了  乔  谁雇了你
Cut the corners, Joe. Who hired you?
是你妹妹
It was your sister.
乔
Joe...
我没有妹妹
I don't have a sister.
-后来呢  -不知道  口供就到这儿
- What happens next? - I don't know. That's the end of the statement.
可如果莎莉不是薇拉的妹妹  她是谁呢
But if Sally wasn't Vera's sister, then who was she?
莎莉给私家侦探下了套
Sally set up the P.I.
是经典的黑色电影大逆转啊
It's a classic film noir twist.
-可为什么呢  -不知道
- But why? - I don't know.
-莎莉的目的是什么  -不知道
- What was Sally up to? - I don't know.
你觉得她跟丹普西有牵连吗
Do you think she was connected to Dempsey?
不知道  但这是不是太棒了
I don't know, but isn't this great?
贝克特
Yo, Beckett.
巡警找到了那个在佩尼贝克非法居住的
So our uniforms got a line on that homeless guy
流浪汉的线索
who was squatting in the Pennybaker.
卖热狗的小贩认出了他
A hot dog vendor I.D.'ed him.
说他名叫西区瓦利
Said the guy goes by the name of West Side Wally.
我通缉了他
I put a want out on the guy.
很好  那也许是我们抓住
Great. That might be the break we need
杀害斯坦真凶的突破口
to catch Stan's killer.
接个电话
Excuse me.
喂
Hello.
什么
What?
什么时候
When?
好吧  我就出发  多谢
All right. I'm on my way. Thank you.
是斯坦所住酒店的经理打来的
That was the manager of Stan's residency hotel.
一个开着白色野马的男人
A guy driving a white Mustang
刚刚闯进了斯坦的房间
just forced his way into Stan's room,
他还在那儿
and he's still there.
纽约警局  举起手来
NYPD! Show us your hands.
举起手来  现在
Show us your hands. Now!
慢慢转过身来
Turn around slowly.
你是汤姆·丹普西
You're Tom Dempsey.
没错  是我
Yeah, that's me.
汤姆·丹普西三世
Tom Dempsey III.
太像了
Dead ringer.
简直是一个模子刻的
Complete doppelganger.
遗传基因的作用  又不是魔术
It's D.N.A., guys. It's not a magic trick.
我是他孙子
I'm his grandson.
好吧
All right, look.
破门而入我很抱歉
I'm sorry I broke in a door.
我会赔偿损失  没什么大不了
I'll pay for the damages. It's no big deal.
为什么还不放我走
Why am I still here?
我们只是好奇  想看看
Well, we were just curious to see
除了长相  你是否还从你祖父那里
if you inherited anything else from your grandfather,
继承了别的什么
aside from his looks.
是啊  比如你用来杀害斯坦·班克斯的
Yeah, like one of his .38 revolvers that you used
点38左轮手枪
to kill Stan Banks.
等等  不是这样的
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa. That didn't happen.
是斯坦来找我
Look, Stan came to me,
可他告诉我  他名叫纳撒尼尔·詹金斯
only he told me his name was Nathaniel Jenkins.
他说他是个传记作家
He said he was a biographer,
说他想写一个关于我祖父的故事
said he wanted to do a story about my grandfather.
他保证说不会写他的违法交易
He promised not to focus on his underworld dealings,
只侧重好的一面
just on the--the good stuff,
比如说我祖父是社区的支柱
like how my granddad was a pillar of the community.
社区祸害还差不多
More like a killer of the community.
当他这么提议
And so when he made his pitch,
你因为想重塑家族名望  就答应配合了
you, wanting to rehabilitate your family name, cooperated.
是的
Yeah.
我给他看了祖父留下的所有旧文件
I gave him access to all of granddad's old papers,
一切进展顺利
and everything was cool...
直到我发现这整件事都是个谎言
until I found out the whole thing was a lie.
你怎么发现的
And how'd you do that?
过去在我祖父的俱乐部里
There's this singer who used to
有个红极一时的歌手
headline at my granddad's club--
叫贝西·辛克莱
Betsy Sinclair.
几周前  她过世了
Couple weeks ago, she passed away.
我前去悼念
Well, I went there to pay my respects,
在那里看见了纳撒尼尔
and who do I see there but Nathaniel,
正跟个老头聊天
chatting up this old guy.
他看见了我  立马从后面跑了
He sees me, jets out the back.
我完全不明白这是怎么回事
I'm like, "What the hell is this all about," right?
所以我查看了来宾名单
So I look in the guest book.
才发现
I figured it out.
他所签的真名是  斯坦·班克斯
He'd signed his real name-- Stan Banks.
你就知道他不是传记作家
Which is when you figured out he wasn't really a biographer.
他只是又一个卑鄙的寻宝猎人
He was just another lowlife treasure hunter,
在找蓝蝴蝶的下落
looking for the blue butterfly.
再说  如果有谁该得到蓝蝴蝶
And if anybody deserved the blue butterfly,
那人理应是你  对吗
it was you, right?
所以你跟踪了斯坦
So you followed Stan.
斯坦找到了它的下落  你就枪杀了他
And when stan found it, you shot him.
不  我没有  我没有对他开枪
No, I did not-- I did not shoot him.
斯坦  等等  斯坦找到了
Stan--wait. Stan did find it?
得了  别装了
Come on. You tell us.
我真不知道  我不在场
I don't know. I was not there.
我看报  发现他死了
I read in the newspaper that the guy was dead.
我就去他的公寓  看看能有什么发现
I went to his apartment to see what I could find.
我没有杀他
And I didn't kill the guy.
丹普西的不在场证明成立
So Dempsey's alibi holds up.
他没有杀斯坦
He didn't kill Stan.
没关系  我们有突破口了
Well, that's all right, because we caught a break.
警员终于追踪到了西区瓦利的下落
Unis finally tracked down West Side Wally.
正带他过来问话
They're bringing him in now.
很好  也许这能对弄清斯坦的遭遇
Great. Maybe that can shed some light
有所帮助
as to what happened to Stan.
如果他不能  也许杰瑞·马多克斯可以
And if he can't, maybe Jerry Maddox can.
杰瑞·马多克斯
Jerry Maddox?
你还记得汤姆三世告诉我们
You remember how Tom III told us that Stan
斯坦去过贝西·辛克莱的葬礼吗
went to Betsy Sinclair's funeral?
我在想  他为什么去那儿
I started thinking, why would he go?
去调查啊
To do research.
没错  可是调查谁呢
Right, but research on whom?
于是我去了葬礼会客厅
So I stopped by the funeral parlor.
结果发现斯坦与死者的友人杰瑞·马多克斯
Turns out that Stan spent an awful lot of time
聊了好一段时间
with a friend of the deceased named Jerry Maddox.
而关键是
And get this--
杰瑞曾是佩尼贝克俱乐部的老酒保
Jerry was the old bartender at the Pennybaker Club,
他大概是蓝蝴蝶最后一条有迹可循的线索
And probably the last living link to the Blue Butterfly.
做的好  卡塞尔
Good job, Castle.
是吗
Yeah?
是啊
Yeah.
杰瑞
Jerry.
这是贝克特警探和卡塞尔先生
This is Detective Beckett and Mr. Castle.
他们想聊聊
They wanted a word.
当然可以
Oh, yeah.
你们想来点汤吗  自家炖的
You want some soup? It's homemade.
我倒乐意来一碗  闻起来很香
Oh, I don't mind if I do. That smells delicious.
不用  谢了  不必麻烦了
Uh, no, thank you. Actually, we're--we're all right.
这首歌是不是
Am I hearing
《我能给予你的只有爱》
"I Can't Give You Anything But Love"?
没错  孩子
That's right, kid.
那也是这首歌最好的版本
That's the best version of that tune, too.
你们不是来聊音乐的吧
You come here to talk music, did you?
其实  我们是来调查斯坦·班克斯的谋杀案的
Actually, we're here to investigate Stan Bank's murder,
我们想知道你是否在贝西·辛克莱的葬礼上
And we were wondering if you met him
遇到过他
at Betsy Sinclair's funeral.
是的  他  他被杀了吗
Yeah. He--he was murdered?
可怜的孩子
Poor kid.
他有没有提到一条叫做蓝蝴蝶的项链
Did he mention a necklace called the Blue Butterfly?
当然  他问了我很多问题
Oh, sure. Asked me all kinds of questions.
它可能在哪儿  之类的问题
Uh, where it might be, stuff like that,
可我那时只是个酒保
but I was just a bartender back then.
我帮不上他
I-I wasn't much help.
下面这个问题  可能听上去很奇怪
Now this might seem an odd question,
但在1947年  薇拉·莫奎恩和乔·弗林
But in 1947, do you remember when Vera Mulqueen
被杀的事  你是否还记得
and Joe Flynn were murdered?
当然  那在当时引起很大轰动
Of course. It was a big deal back then.
那家俱乐部的所有者  丹普西
Dempsey, the fella that owned the club,
残忍地枪杀了他们
shot them in cold blood.
同一年  您还记不记得
The same year, do you remember
有个名叫莎莉·斯科菲尔德的女人
a woman named sally scofield?
她一头红发
She was a redhead.
1947年  她大概是18岁
In 1947, she would've been about 18.
我想我知道你在说谁了
Oh, I think I know who you're talking about.
那是在46年
Now that's back in '46.
我刚被佩尼贝克雇用
I had just got hired at the Pennybaker.
卖香烟啦  雪茄
Cigarettes. Cigars.
那时丹普西还没跟薇拉在一起
Dempsey wasn't dating vera back then.
他那时的女伴名叫普丽西拉·卡贝尔
He was going with a gal named Priscilla Campbell.
普丽西拉有个女儿
Priscilla had a daughter,
名叫莎莉的红发女孩
a redhead named Sally.
听起来她就是你说的那个
Sounds like she's the one you mean.
后来发生的事  就是个悲剧
Sad story, what happened.
不久后  薇拉吸引了丹普西的视线
Not long after vera caught dempsey's eye,
他抛弃了普丽西拉
he dropped Priscilla
无情地断绝了与她和莎莉的往来
and cut her and Sally off cold.
他们说这就是蓝蝴蝶的诅咒
They said it was the curse of the Blue Butterfly.
普丽西拉服药自杀了
Priscilla killed herself with a handful of pills.
莎莉呢
And Sally?
几个月之后
Couple months after, uh,
薇拉和那个私人侦探被杀
Vera and that P.I. got whacked,
丹普西死于心脏病
Dempsey died of a heart attack.
他葬礼的那晚
The evening of his funeral,
莎莉盛装来到俱乐部
in walks Sally, all dressed up.
点了一杯纯威士忌
Ordered a whiskey neat,
一干而尽
slammed it back,
对我露齿冷笑
gave me a big ol' crocodile grin,
说她自由了
Said she was free.
然后昂首阔步地出了门
Then she strutted on out the door,
那是我最后一次见到她
and that's the last time I ever saw her.
这是个复仇的故事
It's a revenge story.
莎莉将其母亲之死归罪于薇拉
Sally blamed Vera for the death of her mother,
密谋杀害她
so she plotted to take her down.
她利用私家侦探
Somehow she used the P.I. to do it.
他俩肯定是被她陷害的
She must have been setting them up.
是的  但这对找出杀害斯坦的凶手
Yeah, but how does any of this help us figure out
有什么帮助吗
who shot Stan?
那么
So...
西区瓦利
West Side Wally.
能叫你瓦利吗
May I call you Wally?
我比较喜欢别人叫我西区
I prefer West Side.
好吧
Of course.
西区  我们知道两天前你在佩尼贝克俱乐部
West Side, we know you were at the Pennybaker Club two days ago.
我们发现了你的"窝"
Yeah, we found your squat.
卡妮  蕾希  你们可以就此打住了
Cagney and Lacey, you can stop right there.
两天前我没住在俱乐部
I wasn't living in the club two days ago.
有人给我钱请我出去住
I had already gotten bought out by the other guy.
-给你钱  -什么人
- Bought out? - By the other guy?
几天前  有个人进来
A few days ago, the other guy comes in,
开始在酒吧搭窝
starts setting up a squat by the bar,
但西区瓦利不喜欢与人同住
but West Side Wally doesn't do neighbors.
于是我说"教授  滚远点"
So I said, "Hey, Professor, kick rocks."
可他就是不走
He wouldn't take no for an answer.
反而给了四百刀让我另觅住所
Ended up paying me $400 to relocate.
重申一次  那天我不在
So again, for the record this time, I wasn't there.
冷静点  好吗  你知道那人叫什么吗
Easy, easy, okay. Did you get this guy's name?
我没问  他也没说
I didn't ask. He didn't say.
能描述下他的样子吗
Can you describe him?
中等身高  不胖不瘦  白人  50岁左右
Medium height, medium build, white, 50s.
我叫他教授
I called him the Professor
他讲话就像个矫饰做作的蠢蛋
because he spoke like a pretentious jerk.
对  这不是教授嘛
Hey, it's the Professor.
克莱德·贝拉斯科
Clyde Belasco.
我们知道你去过佩尼贝克俱乐部
We know that you were at the Pennybaker Club,
贝拉斯科先生
Mr. Belasco.
你用钱把流浪汉打发走
You paid off a homeless man
这样你就能独自占着那地方
so that you could have the place to yourself.
我在上东区有处豪华公寓
I have a condo on the upper east side,
在波尔多[法国西南部港市]有座城堡
a chateau in Bordeaux,
在格斯塔德[瑞士滑雪胜地]有座农舍
a chalet in Gstaad, and yet.
仅凭某个流浪汉的片面之词
On the word of some vagrant,
你就断定我用钱打发他
you believe that I paid to
好让自己在荒废的地方搭窝
squat in an abandoned building?
我可是大名鼎鼎的克莱德·贝拉斯科
Me? Clyde Belasco?
我们就是这个意思
Pretty much.
先生  我倒想看看你怎么证明
I'd like to see you prove it, sir.
好啊  教授  听你的
All right, have it your way, Professor.
我们庭审宣判见吧
We will see you at the sentencing hearing.
你可以在监狱里做你的电视节目
You can do your TV show from prison.
等等
Wait.
好吧我说
Okay.
我承认  我在那
I was there. I admit it.
斯坦被杀之时我在佩尼贝克俱乐部
I was at the Pennybaker Club when Stan was killed.
但他不是我杀的
But I didn't kill him.
如我之前所说  斯坦来找我
Like I said before, Stan came to me
问我要
and asked for my research
蓝蝴蝶的研究报告
on the Blue Butterfly.
你拒绝了吗
And you said no?
我当然拒绝了
Of course I said no.
我花了15年的时间去找那条项链
I searched for that necklace for 15 years,
而现在要我去帮他
and now I'm just supposed to help him?
这份荣耀只属于我
The glory was to be mine.
但你知道他找到了线索  对吗
But you knew he was on to something, didn't you?
对
Oh, yes.
我看得出他已离成功不远  非常接近
I could tell he was close, so very close.
斯坦知道我从没听说过的
Stan knew things about the club, about the necklace
关于俱乐部和项链的事
that I had never heard before.
所以你在俱乐部那侯着
So you staked out the club,
斯坦一出现 你就把他杀了
and when Stan showed, you shot him.
探长  我没杀他
I didn't shoot him, Detective.
我随身都带着把手枪和一条牛鞭
Yes, I had a pistol with me and a bullwhip.
它们就是我的标志  众所周知
They're my trademarks. Everyone knows that.
但我还带了面具和手套
But I brought a mask and gloves as well
我纯粹只想吓唬吓唬他
because I was simply going to threaten him
窃取他的成果
and take the prize.
后来呢
So then what happened?
我躺在那等着他
I was lying in wait.
斯坦下楼  当他回来的时候  他
Stan went downstairs, and when he returned, he was...
手握蓝蝴蝶
holding the Blue Butterfly.
你们真该看看它有多璀璨
Oh, you should've seen how it sparkled.
完美无瑕
Magnificent.
我正打算扑抢的时候
I was about to pounce
突然有人用布捂住我的嘴
when suddenly there was a-a rag put over my mouth.
甜甜的味道
It had a sweet smell,
布上好像洒了氯仿
like it was doused with chloroform.
氯仿
Chloroform?
-真的吗  -绝对是
- Really? - It had to be.
然后我眼前一黑  我醒来时
Everything went dark, and when I came to,
斯坦已经死了
Stan was dead.
我把他尸体搜了个遍
I searched his body,
肯定是把我弄晕的人拿走了项链
but whoever knocked me out took the Blue Butterfly with them.
我真希望是他
God, I hope it's him.
我也是  但是他不认罪
Yeah, but without a confession,
我们手上的都是间接证据
our case is purely circumstantial.
我试试看能否拿到贝拉斯科住处的搜查令
I'm gonna see if I can get a warrant for Belasco's place.
哪个住处  豪华公寓
Which place, the condo,
城堡  还是农舍
the chateau, or the chalet?
你好  我是凯特·贝克特探长
Hi, yeah, this is Detective Kate Beckett,
12分局
12th Precint.
找区检察官
I'm calling for the riding A.D.A.
好的  我等着
Yeah. Okay. I'll hold.
真令我失望
Well, it's kind of disappointing.
我多期盼侦破斯坦的凶杀案
I was really hoping that solving Stan's murder
能给我点答案
would give us some answers
让我知道乔和薇拉身上到底发生了什么
to what really happened to Joe and Vera.
但我们已经知道了
Yeah, but what we already know what really happened.
丹普西把他们俩杀了
Dempsey killed them both.
这是显而易见的
Well, that's obvious version.
但莎莉呢
But what about Sally?
她在整件事中扮演着什么角色  而且
What's her part in all of this? And...
为何他会雇佣乔
why would she hire Joe?
我想我们永远也不可能知道了
Well, I guess we'll never know.
不  事情还没结束
No, something else was going on.
我们遗漏了些事
Something we're missing.
她穿着T字带斜面的鞋  穿着很土的衣服
"Wearing t-strap shoes and a country suit,
我看得出红发女是个刚进城的乡巴佬
I could tell that redhead was a hick off the cob."
等等  你刚说什么
Wait. What did you just say?
这是乔日记里对她的描述
Well, that's just how Joe described her in his diary.
不  鞋那部分
No, the--the part about the shoes?
T字带  就是鞋带绕过
T-strap. It's when the strap comes over the--
我能待会再打给你吗
Yeah. Can I just call you back?
好的
Okay.
看看这张照片
Take a look at this photo.
车旁边有只鞋
There's a shoe next to the car.
仔细看看那鞋的样式
And look at what kind of shoe it is.
T字带
That's a T-strap.
你不会想说
You don't think...
如果薇拉当晚在俱乐部
If Vera was at the club that night,
她会身着礼服
she'd be dressed in an elegant dress and...
高跟鞋  死的不是薇拉
And heels. This isn't Vera.
死的是莎莉
This is Sally.
也不可能是莎莉
Yeah, but it can't be Sally.
酒保说案发后几个月他还见过莎莉
The bartender said that he saw her months after the murders.
-除非他说谎  -他说谎
- Unless... he lied. - He lied.
但那是半个多世纪前的事了
But that was over half a century ago.
他为何如此
Why would he lie about that?
贝克特  我刚刚意识到一件事
Beckett, I just realized something.
《我能给予你的只有爱》
"I Can't Give You Anything But Love."
什么意思
W-what?
我们询问酒保时  播放的那首歌
That's what was playing when we interviewed the bartender.
对  我想起来了
Right. Right.
他说那是这首歌最好的版本
He said that that was the best version of the song.
这是路易斯·阿姆斯特朗[美国爵士歌手]的版本
It was Louis Armstrong's version.
乔的日记里  他说他最爱的歌手是沙奇摩
In Joe's diary, he says his favorite performer is Satchmo.
沙奇摩的真名是
What's Satchmo's real name?
路易斯·阿姆斯特朗
Louis Armstrong.
全部联系起来
Put it all together,
答案很明晰了
the answer is clear.
又见面了
Oh. Hello again.
薇拉你好
Hello, Vera.
乔你好
And hello, Joe.
薇拉·莫奎恩和乔·弗林
Well, if it isn't Vera Mulqueen and Joe Flynn,
起死回生
back from the dead.
一切都好吗
Everything all right, guys?
一切都好  多谢关心  弗兰基
Everything's peachy. Thanks, Frankie.
怎么回事  斯坦发现真相了吗
What happened? Stan figured out the truth,
发现你俩还活着
that you two were alive,
发现你们为了偷走蓝蝴蝶
that you murdered two people
而杀了两个人吗
so you could disappear with the Blue Butterfly?
于是你们就把他骗到俱乐部然后杀了他吗
So you lured him to the club and then you shot him?
小姐  你的推测全错了
Lady, you got it all wrong.
斯坦在贝西的葬礼上缠住了我
Stan cornered me at Betsy's funeral,
想知道我是怎么认识她的
wanting to know how I knew her.
于是我只好骗他说我是当时的酒保
So I lied and told him I was a bartender.
但是斯坦很聪明  他太聪明了
But Stan was clever. He was too clever.
他把我们识破了
He figured us out.
他跑来这里逼我们说出
He came here demanding to know
蓝蝴蝶的下落
where the Blue Butterfly was.
他威胁说要告发我们
He threatened to expose us.
他不达目的绝不善罢甘休
He was like a dog after a bone.
所以我们就满足了他的要求
So we told him what he needed to know.
我们把蓝蝴蝶的下落告诉他了
We told him where it was.
但是我们并没有杀他
But we didn't kill him.
得了  伙计们
Oh, come on, you guys.
肯定是你们俩干的
We know it's you.
你们用了1947年犯案的同一把枪
You used the same gun from the '47 murders to kill Stan.
同一把枪  我们一直把那把枪放在
Same gun? Oh, we keep that gun in the --
装瓷器的碗橱里
The china cabinet drawer.
你想都别想
Don't even think about it.
把枪放下
Put the gun down.
弗兰西斯·本杰明·亨特沙克
Francis Benjamin Huntsacker,
你都干了什么呀
what have you done?
等一下  亨特沙克
Wait a minute. Huntsacker?
正是你母亲把那本日记卖给了斯坦
It was your mother who sold the diary to Stan.
什么日记
What diary?
你的日记
Your diary.
这么说你看过那本日记
So you read it,
而一直以来你也在寻找那条项链的下落
and all this time, you were looking for the necklace, too.
不然我为什么干这烂工作
That's why I got this crap job.
六个月以来  我慢慢使你们信任我
And for six months, I slowly built trust,
渐渐地从你们的嘴里套话
gently acquired information.
结果那混蛋就这么闯进来
And then that jerk just waltzes in here
逼你们说出了项链的下落
and bullies the location of the Blue Butterfly from you?
拜托
Come on!
当你意识到这是最后的机会时
So when you realized it was now or never,
你伏击了斯坦
you bushwhacked Stan,
然后抢走了蓝蝴蝶
took the Blue Butterfly for yourself?
我带上枪就是为了以防万一
I brought their old .38 only as a precaution.
我只想把斯坦迷晕然后从他那偷走蓝蝴蝶
I was just gonna chloroform Stan and steal it.
但你却发现克莱德·贝拉斯科藏在吧台后面
But you found Clyde Belasco hiding behind the bar.
我拔出了枪  斯坦冲了上来
I pulled the gun, Stan grabbed for it...
听着  我不是故意的
Look, I didn't mean to.
走吧  弗兰基  你被捕了
Let's go, Frankie. You're under arrest.
卡塞尔  你猜我们在弗兰基的公寓里
Hey, Castle, guess what we found
找到了什么
at Frankie's apartment.
天啊
Oh, my.
Oh, my god.
太美了
It's beautiful.
-是个赝品  -你说什么
- It's fake.  - What?
我们已经把它拿去鉴定过了
We confirmed it with an appraiser.
这只是手工精良的人造珠宝而已
It's well-crafted costume jewelry.
这么多人费了这么大劲  就为这吗
All this time, and it's paste?
这还真是
That's...
又或者峰回路转又一村
Or maybe it's a twist on a twist.
也许真正的蓝蝴蝶
Maybe the real Blue Butterfly
在多年前就被人掉包了
was switched out for this one years ago.
不管怎样  摆在我们面前的事实都是一样的
Well, whatever happened, it doesn't change the facts.
我们还有案子没结呢
We still have one more case to close.
现在我们知道
Okay, so now we know
杀害斯坦的凶手是弗兰基
that Frankie killed Stan,
但是我们还有两宗谋杀案未破呢
but there are still two murders that need to be solved --
也就是莎莉·坎贝尔和被你们丢在汽车里的另一具尸体
Sally Campbell and whoever else you put in that car.
你们现在该老实交代1947年6月24日的晚上
It's time you come clean on what happened
到底发生了什么
the evening of June 24, 1947,
也就是你们失踪的那晚
The night you disappeared.
告诉他们吧  薇拉
Tell them, Vera.
我们都挤在收音机前
We were all huddled around the, uh, radio, listening to
收听舒格·雷·罗宾逊对战吉米·度耶的职业拳击赛
the Sugar Ray Robinson VS Jimmy Doyle prizefight, and, uh,
而我一直在为逃跑的计划而坐立不安
I was building up nerve to make my escape.
将两人分开
...breaks up the clinch.
渐渐疲劳的吉米·度耶挥出一记左拳  又是一拳
A slowly tiring Jimmy Doyle throws a left, another left.
接下来是罗宾逊
Here comes Robinson.
一记左拳  一记右拳  又一记左拳
A left. A right. Another left...
莫克西  我要去洗手间
Moxie, I need to powder my nose.
你开什么玩笑  非得现在去吗
Are you kidding me? Can it wait?
对
No.
听你的  老板
Ah, what do you say, boss?
好吧  快去快回
Yeah, yeah, yeah, make it quick.
罗宾逊改变策略
Robinson regroups.
罗宾逊挥出一记左拳  右拳  接着又是一记左拳
Robinson delivers a left, a right, a left again.
度耶回击  但却被罗宾逊躲了过去
Doyle punches back, but missed him by a mile.
真是天作之合呀
Well, aren't you a picture?
你是谁
Who are you?
我是她男人
I'm with her.
把手举起来
Put 'em up.
那家伙是莎莉的丈夫
The guy was Sally's husband.
她雇用乔只是为了把我从丹普西身边带走
She'd only hired Joe to get me away from Dempsey
她好实施她的复仇计划
so she could exact her revenge.
现在该让你尝尝我母亲所受的苦了
Now you're gonna suffer, Vera, like my mother suffered.
等一下  莎莎  我先去拿项链
Wait, Sal. Let me get the ice first.
不
No!
兰尼
Lenny!
你干吗
Ugh! What are you doing?
把枪给我
Give me the gun!
乔
Oh! Joe!
我们本就深陷泥潭
We were hot as a pistol
这下我们手上又多了两条人命
and -- and we had two bodies on our hands,
我们不得不想点办法
And we had to do something.
而乔
And Joe...
想出了一个完美计划
had the plan.
没人会去寻找那两个人的下落
No one would be looking for those two.
而我们正好需要消失
We needed to disappear.
显然  我们隐藏的不够好
Obviously, we didn't disappear far enough.
那么
So...
你要逮捕我们吗
are you going to arrest us?
我逮捕你们干吗
Why would I do that?
听上去你们是在自卫
Sounds like self-defense.
再说
Besides...
我们要找的是一个叫做薇拉
we're looking for a woman named Vera,
而不是维奥拉
not Viola,
要找的是私家侦探乔
And a P.I. named Joe,
而不是前酒保杰瑞
not a former bartender named Jerry.
我们真不知道该怎么感谢你们
We don't know how to thank you.
我知道
I do.
回答我两个问题
Answer two questions.
第一
One...
拿到了蓝蝴蝶  为什么没带走
if you had the Blue Butterfly, why didn't you take it?
第二
And two...
它到底在哪儿
where has it been all this time?
我们本来是要拿走蓝蝴蝶的  可这位美人
Well, we were home free till doll face here
突然间顿悟了
had herself an epiphany.
这东西的确是被诅咒了
This thing really is cursed.
薇拉  那只是吊在绳子上的漂亮石头而已
Vera, that's just fancy rocks on a pretty rope.
不  不只是石头
No, it's more than that.
是苦痛的源头  乔  我们不能带走它
It's misery. Joe, we can't.
我不在乎这东西
I got no love for this thing,
我爱的只有你
Just you.
但是我也决不会
But I'll be damned
让这东西再落到丹普西手里
if I let Dempsey get his hands back on it.
那混蛋这辈子都不会知道
Let the bastard spend the rest of his life
他的宝贝就藏在他的眼皮底下
not knowing his prize possession is right under his nose.
抛开诅咒不提  你们没想过回去拿回来吗
Cursed or not, did you ever consider going back for it?
他们还是不明白  乔
They don't get it, Joe.
我
Mm. I...
我们有四个孩子
We got four children,
七个孙子孙女
seven grandchildren,
两个曾孙曾孙女
two great-grandchildren...
还有彼此
and each other.
我们要蓝蝴蝶干吗
What do we need a Blue Butterfly for?
你觉得我们是不是应该把蓝蝴蝶的真相
Do you think we should've told Joe and Vera
告诉乔和薇拉
about the Blue Butterfly?
不  何必毁了这一切呢
Oh, no. Why ruin it for them?
梦想就是用来干这个的
No, that's the stuff that dreams are made of.
说你爱我  乔
Tell me you love me, Joe.
我会永远爱你
Always.